Brothers and sisters,
兄弟姉妹 お会いできてうれしく思います
welcome to this update!
The Omicron variant of the COVID-19 virus
新型コロナウイルスのオミクロン株の
感染が世界中で急速に広がっています
has quickly spread throughout the world.
The number of cases has exploded.
感染者数は爆発的に増加しています
We’re saddened to report
残念なことに 1月21日 金曜日の時点で
that as of Friday, January 21,
26,813 of our brothers
2万6813人の兄弟姉妹が
新型コロナウイルスで亡くなっています
have now died from COVID-19.
But there have been
some encouraging developments.
でも こういう報告もあります
For those who are vaccinated,
ワクチンを受けたほとんどの人は
オミクロン株に感染しても
cases of Omicron are generally milder
それほど重症化せず 入院や死に
至ってはいません
and have not led to hospitalization or death.
For example, you may have heard reports
例えばプエルトリコでは
オミクロン株の感染が急速に
拡大しました
that there has been a major outbreak
of Omicron in Puerto Rico.
プエルトリコはワクチン接種率が
非常に高いことでも知られています
You may also know that Puerto Rico
has a very high rate of vaccination.
Although 551 cases were reported
今回の感染拡大によって
551人の兄弟姉妹が感染しましたが
亡くなったのは3人です
among our brothers
during the recent outbreak,
only three of our brothers have died.
And it is our understanding that all of them
報告によると 3人とも重い基礎疾患を
抱えていたようです
had serious underlying health issues.
Even one death is too many,
私たちはこの感染症によって
一人も亡くなることを望んでいません
yet we’re relieved that so few died.
Our hearts go out to all
who have lost loved ones.
愛する人を亡くした皆さんのために
心から祈っています
Please continue to be careful.
パンデミックはまだ終わっていないので
これからも注意を払いましょう
The pandemic is not over,
and we need to continue
to take practical steps
命と健康を守るために これからも
感染対策を続ける必要があります
to protect our lives and our health.
In addition to the pandemic,
世界ではパンデミックに加え
さまざまな大変な出来事が生じています
it has been sobering
to watch recent world events unfold.
We see one natural disaster after another,
自然災害があちこちで生じています
戦争が起きる可能性もあります
and we hear threats of war.
“The king of the north”
and “the king of the south”
「北の王」と「南の王」は
今も「押し合」っています
continue “pushing” one another.
When we hear all these things
happening in the world,
世界中の出来事について考えると
「ずっと見張ってい」ることが
it reminds us how vital it is
that we “keep on the watch”.
非常に大切であることが分かります
We need to stay awake spiritually
注意を怠らず 気を散らされないように
しなければなりません
and not doze off or get distracted.
Why?
なぜですか
Because we are living
in the most critical time in human history.
今は 人類史上最も危機的な時だからです
Jesus knew that the last days
would bring challenges
イエスは クリスチャンが
終わりの時代にさまざまな問題に
that would test our spiritual focus.
ぶつかることを知っていました
Out of his deep love, he urged his followers
それで深い愛に動かされ
ルカ 21:34-36にある警告を与えました
as recorded at Luke chapter 21
verses 34-36:
“But pay attention to yourselves
「とはいえ 食べ過ぎや飲み過ぎや
“that your hearts never become weighed down
生活上の心配事で心が圧迫されないよう
注意していなさい
“with overeating and heavy drinking
and anxieties of life,
そうでないと その日が
全く突然に訪れます
“and suddenly that day
be instantly upon you as a snare.
わなのようにです
その日は地上の全ての人に訪れます
“For it will come upon all those dwelling
on the face of the whole earth.
“Keep awake, then,
all the time making supplication
それで 必ず起きるこの全てのことを
逃れて人の子の前に立つことができるよう
“that you may succeed
in escaping all these things
常に祈願をしつつ
ずっと目を覚ましていなさい」
that must occur and in standing
before the Son of man.”
We constantly hear encouraging reports
兄弟姉妹はエホバに一生懸命に仕え
「ずっと目を覚ましてい」ます
that you dear brothers and sisters
are working hard to “keep awake”
私たちはいつも 励みになる報告を
受け取っています
and remain busy in your service to Jehovah.
You’re busy in your personal ministry
皆さんは熱心に伝道しています
手紙を書いたり 電話をしたりしています
—writing letters, making phone calls,
and looking for opportunities
to share the good news informally—
生活のさまざまな場面で
良い知らせを伝えています
and many were able to auxiliary pioneer
最近のキャンペーンでは
多くの人が補助開拓奉仕をしました
during the recent campaign.
Staying busy in Jehovah’s service
is a protection for us.
エホバに一生懸命仕えることは
身の守りになります
But more is required to protect our hearts.
でも 心を守るにはさらに努力が必要です
It’s vital for all of us to “keep awake”
私たち全ては「ずっと目を覚ましてい」て
—to be watchful of things
エホバとの絆を弱めるものに
警戒する必要があります
that could pose a danger to us spiritually.
What are some of these dangers?
何に警戒すべきですか
Jesus mentioned things
like “overeating and heavy drinking
イエスは 「食べ過ぎや飲み過ぎや
生活上の心配事」を挙げています
and anxieties of life.”
What are some ways
that these things could cause our hearts
こうしたことによって
「心が圧迫され」ることがあります
to “become weighed down”?
どのようにでしょうか
First, let’s talk
about one common cause for anxiety
今 多くの人が心配や不安を
感じているのはなぜですか
—social isolation.
原因の1つは孤独感です
No doubt we have never felt as isolated
パンデミック中 私たちは人々と
自由に接することができません
as we have during this pandemic.
True, it has been necessary
to isolate ourselves physically
もちろん 新型コロナウイルスの感染を
避けるためには 人との接触を
控える必要があります
to prevent the spread of COVID-19.
But if we’re not careful,
でも注意しないと 人との接触を
過度に控えてしまうかもしれません
we could start
to isolate ourselves in other ways.
Maybe at times, we feel Zoom fatigue,
もしかすると時折 Zoom疲れを感じて
and we even want
to isolate ourselves virtually.
オンラインでも人に会いたくないと
思うかもしれません
What’s the danger?
どんな危険がありますか
Proverbs 18:1 says:
格言 18:1にはこうあります
“Whoever isolates himself
「自分を孤立させる人は
自分の欲求ばかり満たそうとし
“pursues his own selfish desires;
he rejects all practical wisdom.”
あらゆる役立つ知恵を退ける」
It takes effort to reach out
to our brothers by telephone,
確かに 電話やビデオ通話やメールで
by videoconference,
or even with an email or text message,
兄弟姉妹に連絡を取るには
努力が要ります
でもそういう努力をすると
自分の方が元気をもらえます
but so often the encouragement
that we receive from doing so
ですから 努力する価値があります
makes the effort so worthwhile.
Often, we receive back
more than what we may have given.
与えたものより多くのものを受ける場合が
少なくありません
イエスが使徒 20:35で言っている通りです
Just as Jesus said at Acts 20:35:
“There is more happiness in giving
「受けるより与える方が幸福である」
than there is in receiving.”
An article on jw.org entitled
jw.orgの「寂しいと感じたら」という
記事には 興味深いことが書かれています
“How to Deal With Isolation”
made an interesting point
under the heading
「人とのつながりを大切にする」
という見出しです
“Cultivate friendships”:
“Friendships benefit
your mental and emotional health
「友達がいると心が落ち着き
前向きになれます
“and are even more important
when face-to-face connections are difficult.
直接会えないときでも友達との
つながりを保つのは大切です
“If you are confined at home,
家から出られないときには
ビデオ通話や電話などで友達と会話し
“you may be able to use videoconferencing
“or voice calls
to maintain existing friendships
交友の輪を広げることができます」
and build new ones.”
私たちには友が必要です
友も私たちを必要としています
We need our brothers and sisters,
and they need us!
To have a friend, we must be a friend.
友達が欲しいなら
友達にならなければなりません
So be a friend!
こちらから行動しましょう
Could you reach out to someone this week?
今週 誰かと連絡が取れますか
Perhaps you can think of a friend
最近話せていない友達がいるなら
連絡してみるのはどうですか
whom you haven’t been able
to talk with for some time.
The joy of speaking with your friend
友達と話し 楽しい時を過ごすなら
きっと穏やかな気持ちになれるでしょう
will no doubt calm
some of the anxieties in your heart.
We can’t wait to get back
to our Kingdom Halls, Assembly Halls,
私たちは王国会館や大会ホールで
兄弟姉妹にじかに会える時を
心待ちにしています
to have our large regional conventions,
地区大会や特別大会や国際大会も
楽しみにしています
special conventions,
and even international conventions.
In the meantime, we are grateful
that we have other means
それまでの間 他の方法で
そうしたプログラムを
楽しむことができます
to enjoy these programs, such as Zoom,
ZoomやJW Streamや場所によっては
テレビやラジオでです
JW Stream and, in some cases,
TV and radio.
ほとんどの会衆は Zoomを使って
集会を開いています
Of course, most congregations
are using Zoom for their meetings.
Isn’t it encouraging
to see our brothers’ and sisters’ faces?
兄弟姉妹の顔を見ることが
できるのはうれしいことです
We appreciate
being able to see them comment
コメントしたり 心を込めて
歌ったりしている様子を
and see them singing from the heart.
見ることができます
This also helps us
to fight feelings of isolation.
こうしたことも孤独感を
和らげる助けになります
Simply turning your camera on and smiling,
カメラをオンにして 温かくほほ笑み
even a simple wave,
手を振るだけでも兄弟姉妹を
元気づけることができます
can be such an encouragement to others.
And we can make it our goal to connect early
できれば早めにZoomに入り
集会後もしばらくとどまりましょう
and stay longer after the meeting.
We can enjoy visiting
with the friends in breakout rooms.
ブレイクアウトルームで
交友を楽しむこともできます
Brothers and sisters,
these are some practical ways
兄弟姉妹 このような方法で
孤独感と闘うことができます
that we can fight back
against feelings of isolation
不安な気持ちを和らげ
and the anxiety that isolation
穏やかな気持ちを保つことが
できるでしょう
can create in our hearts.
Another danger
that Jesus mentioned was heavy drinking.
イエスが警告したもう1つのことは
飲み過ぎることです
Of course, there’s nothing wrong
もちろん 適度にお酒を飲むのは
悪いことではありません
with drinking alcohol in moderation.
The Scriptures describe wine
as a gift from God,
聖書によれば ぶどう酒は
「心を喜びで満たす」神からの贈り物です
designed to make the “heart rejoice.”
But some caution is needed.
でも注意が必要です
なぜですか
Why?
Remember, Jesus specifically cautioned
イエスは何と警告していたでしょうか
that our hearts
could become “weighed down
「飲み過ぎ⋯⋯で心が圧迫されないよう
注意していなさい」と言いました
with . . . heavy drinking.”
Secular reports indicate that many people
幾つかの調査によると パンデミック中
have increased their alcohol consumption
during the pandemic.
多くの人のアルコール消費量は
増えているようです
The article “Alcohol Consumption
—How Can You Stay in Control?”
jw.orgの「飲み過ぎないためには？」
の記事には こう書かれています
on jw.org states:
「ストレスを感じたり 寂しかったり
退屈だったりすると お酒をたくさん
“Some people drink more alcohol
“when they feel stressed,
lonely, or simply bored.
飲んでしまうことがあります
“Are you drinking more than you used to?
最近お酒の量が増えていますか
“If so, how can you make sure
飲み過ぎたり アルコール依存症に
なったりしないために
“that your drinking does not get out of hand
or lead to alcohol dependence?”
どうしたらよいでしょうか」
Even if a person does not get drunk,
たとえ酔わないようにしていても
immoderate drinking
can pose spiritual dangers.
飲み過ぎるならエホバとの関係が
危険にさらされます
Isaiah 5:11 says:
イザヤ 5:11にはこうあります
“Woe to those who get up early
in the morning to drink alcohol,
「酒を飲むために朝早く起きる人たちには災いがある！
“who linger late into the evening darkness
彼らは夕方遅くまで
だらだらと過ごし ぶどう酒にのまれる」
until wine inflames them!”
Why these woes?
災いとあります
Note the spiritual consequences
in the second half of verse 12:
12節の後半には エホバとの関係が
どうなるかが書かれています
“They do not consider
the activity of Jehovah,
「彼らはエホバの行いについて考えず
その方の偉業を見ようともしない」
and they do not see the work of his hands.”
Immoderate drinking
can weigh our hearts down
お酒を飲み過ぎると 心が圧迫されて
エホバへの崇拝に身が入らなくなります
and cause us to neglect spiritual things.
It can cause us
to slow down in the race for life
命を目指す競走のペースが落ち
走るのをやめてしまうかもしれません
or even to stop running altogether.
No wonder Jesus specifically mentioned it
だからこそイエスは
目を覚ましているよう警告した時
when discussing the need
to keep awake spiritually.
飲み過ぎに注意するようにと言ったのです
Why not review that article on jw.org,
このjw.orgの記事を読み返すよう
お勧めします
which features five tips
飲み過ぎないためにできる
5つのことが挙げられています
to help us keep alcohol in its proper place?
ぜひ 参考にしてください
ほかにどんなことが エホバとの関係を
弱める可能性がありますか
What is another potential danger
to our spiritual alertness?
Misuse of social media.
SNSの良くない使い方です
There’s been a lot of concern
from governmental and medical authorities
行政や医療の関係者たちは SNSが
about the effect that social media
人の心の健康に与える影響について
大きな懸念を抱いています
is having on people’s
mental and emotional health.
Even more important
are the spiritual concerns:
クリスチャンには
ほかにも考えるべきことがあります
the content, the people,
and the amount of time involved.
SNSで見るものや 関わる人や
費やす時間です
It can be addictive.
のめり込まないようにしましょう
Brothers and sisters,
if you decide to allow your family
親の皆さん お子さんに
SNSを使うことを許す場合
to use social media, please be alert.
十分に注意してください
Make sure you have good association
SNS上であれ じかに会う場合であれ
with those who promote good spiritual habits,
エホバへの奉仕を後押ししてくれる
友達と一緒に過ごしましょう
whether on screen or off.
The whiteboard animation
Be Social-Network Smart
「SNSをスマートに」という
ホワイトボード･アニメには
provides some good reminders
SNSを使う際にどんな点に注意できるか
役立つ点が取り上げられています
on how to be balanced yet cautious
when using social media.
最後にもう1つの点を考えましょう
What’s the final challenge
we want to consider?
Tests of neutrality.
中立を保つことです
With so many different
challenging situations in the world
世界では さまざまな問題や
対立が生じています
and even the threat of war in some countries,
国によっては
戦争が起きる恐れもあります
we need to be sure
that we are not allowing our hearts
それで 心の中でさえどちらかの側を
支持することがないようにする
必要があります
to take sides on these issues.
How sad it has been
to see simple public health measures
残念なことに マスクの着用 手洗い
like wearing masks, handwashing,
フィジカルディスタンス ワクチン接種
といった基本的な感染症対策が
physical distancing, and vaccinations
議論の種になっています
政治的な問題にさえなっているのです
become controversial, even political!
Some of our brothers and sisters
一部の兄弟姉妹は 周囲の人たちの
政治的な見方の影響を受けているようです
have been influenced by the political views
of those in their community.
Some have turned to the Internet
ウェブサイトの中には
一見信頼できるように見えても
and have been deeply influenced
by official-appearing websites
実際には政治的な考えを
宣伝しているものがあります
filled with highly political propaganda.
Brothers and sisters, be careful.
兄弟姉妹 どうぞ注意してください
Just because something appears
一見信頼できそうな
ウェブサイトだからといって
on an official-looking web page
on the Internet
真実を伝えているとは限りません
does not make it true.
We must guard
against “the spirit of the world”
私たちは「世の精神」と闘い
中立を保つ必要があります
and remain neutral.
How appropriate are Jesus’ words:
ですから イエスの次のアドバイスに
従うことはとても大切です
“Pay attention to yourselves
that your hearts
never become weighed down.”
「心が圧迫されないよう
注意していなさい」
Let’s keep focused on God’s Kingdom
神の王国だけが 世界の問題を
解決できることを
as the only solution
to this world’s problems.
忘れないようにしましょう
What has helped
some families to keep awake?
次のビデオを見てみましょう
クリスチャンの家族は
Let’s see as we watch the following video.
イエスのアドバイスに
どのように従っているでしょうか
During the pandemic,
パンデミックになって
it was definitely difficult
規則正しい生活をするのが
大変だと感じています
to keep a good routine
and it was very easy to form bad habits.
つい だらだらする時間が
増えてしまいます
ずっと家にいるので
パソコンを使う時間が増えました
During isolation,
I spent more time in front of the computer,
and it disturbed my sleep pattern.
夜更かししてしまうこともあります
悪いパターンにはまるのは簡単ですが
抜け出すのはなかなか大変です
I had to make an adjustment
(because with bad habits, you know,
they’re easy to form and hard to break),
それで 良いものと悪いものを
入れ替えることにしました
so I did a little bit
of replacement therapy (I call it),
where you switch from mindless TV watching
例えば テレビでつまらない番組を
見る代わりに ためになる番組を
to something
that’s a little bit more profitable,
見るようにしました
which is our own TV station,
JW Broadcasting®.
JW Broadcasting®です
テレビを長い時間見ていると
As I spent a lot of time watching television,
ワクチンについてのネガティブな情報が
入ってきて 怖くなってしまいました
I heard a lot of negative information
about vaccination.
I was frightened.
メディアからの情報の影響で
I felt pressure from the media,
しばらく前までワクチンは
受けないことにしようと思っていました
and I decided
not to get vaccinated for some time.
エホバに何度も祈って 導きを求めました
We often asked Jehovah for guidance.
ちょうど良い時に
「統治体からの話」を聞きました
The Governing Body updates were timely
and helped us to make the right decisions.
そのおかげで 良い決定を
下すことができました
感謝しています
When the pandemic first started,
I had a lot of free time on my hands,
パンデミックになってから
自由な時間が増えました
so I was just on social media all the time
それで いつもスマホを見たり
SNSを使ったりしていました
or on technology all the time.
Family worship was an excellent opportunity
家族の崇拝で SNSの使い方について
話し合いました
for us to be able to talk about social media
—to really get Jehovah’s thinking on it—
エホバの見方を学んで
バランスを取るようにしました
and how we can balance it
while not eliminating it completely,
全く使わないわけではありませんが
のめり込まないようにしています
so that we controlled it
and it didn’t control us.
It was a slow process,
but eventually I deleted my social media
スマホを使う時間を少しずつ減らして
結局SNSはやめることにしました
and began setting time limits for other apps
ほかのアプリにも結構時間を
取られていたので 時間を決めて
that would take a lot of my time.
使うようにしました
家族で一緒に過ごす時間を増やしました
一緒に音楽やダンスを楽しんだり
Our family decided
to spend more time together.
We played music and danced together.
ゲームをしたり 森に散歩に
行ったりしました
We played board games
and went for walks together in the forest.
That helped us
to reduce the time we used for social media.
そうしたら SNSに使う時間が
自然に減りました
だらだらする時間を
減らすことにしました
I decided to keep my schedule busy,
それで 新しいことを始めました
編み物とか ガーデニングをしています
so I started a few new hobbies,
like knitting and gardening.
正直 Zoomで話すのは
ちょっと苦手なんですけど
I saw a lot of benefit in staying close
to the congregation through Zoom,
会衆のみんなと話していると
元気になれます
even though Zoom is not easy for me.
自分と同じような問題を
経験している人もいるので
Being able to spend time
with people who were going
through the same thing as I was,
いろいろアドバイスをもらえます
was really beneficial.
どのように問題を
乗り越えられるかを話し合います
We could all talk
about what we were dealing with
and encourage each other as well.
とても力になります
We arranged
online Bible-based games through Zoom.{
Zoomを使って 聖書のゲームを
楽しんでいます
I found it nice to use Zoom
to connect with the congregation
時々 会衆の兄弟姉妹が
Zoomのイベントを計画してくれます
for events that were planned
by those in our hall.
とても楽しいです
Some of them were interviews
長年奉仕してきた兄弟姉妹の
インタビューもありました
with those who have been
in our hall for a long time,
いろいろな経験を聞いて
so it was nice to hear those experiences
兄弟姉妹のことを
よく知ることができました
and be able to draw closer to them.
パンデミック中 みんなとよく
コンタクトを取るようにしています
During the pandemic,
I would reach out to others
—either a phone call
or a little card or a text message
電話したり カードやメールを書いたり
家の前に届け物をしたりしています
or just dropping something off
at someone’s door—
みんなとこれまで以上に
親しくなることができました
and it helped me to feel closer
to my brothers and sisters too.
The Governing Body updates
were an absolute lifeline.
「統治体からの話」は
私たちのライフラインです
They were something that really helped us
to focus all of our activity.
クリスチャンの活動に
心を向ける助けになっています
As parents, they helped us
to have clear direction,
親として何をすべきかも
はっきり分かります
so we felt like we were guided
through the whole pandemic
パンデミック中ずっと
必要な導きを受け 力をもらっています
and encouraged at the same time.
I also have been able to see Jehovah
answer my personal prayers even more so
エホバが私の祈りに
答えてくれていることを
これまで以上に実感しています
and see just how he
is holding all of us up
エホバはこの大変な時に
私たちみんなを助けてくれています
during this difficult time,
because I don’t think any of us
エホバの助けがなければ
このパンデミックを
乗り切ることはできません
could get through this pandemic without him.
We are proud of these families
for keeping awake to spiritual dangers.
エホバとの絆を守るため
みんなが一生懸命に頑張っています
Did you notice
how they counteracted social isolation?
孤立しないため どんな努力を
していることに気付きましたか
They have reached out to others regularly.
仲間とよくコンタクトを取っています
They use videoconferencing
ビデオ通話を使って
to stay close
to their congregations and dear friends.
友達や会衆の兄弟姉妹と
話すようにしています
Did you notice how they addressed
their use of social media?
SNSの使い方についてはどうですか
They talked about it as a family
家族みんなで話し合い
and decided either to reduce the time spent
SNSを使う時間を減らすか
全く使わないことにしました
or eliminate it completely.
They have also increased
the time they spend together,
家族で一緒に過ごす時間を増やしました
including enjoyable outdoor activities.
外に出掛けて自然を楽しむ時間も
取っていました
And how did they handle tests of neutrality?
どのように中立の立場を保っていましたか
They prayed to Jehovah
and trusted the information
エホバに祈り
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」から
provided by “the faithful and discreet slave”
与えられる情報を信頼し
よく考えて決定を下していました
in making their own personal decisions.
Very soon, Jehovah’s day
will come upon all the earth.
間もなく エホバの日が来ます
全ての人が影響を受けます
It’s vital that we keep awake.
ですから 注意を怠らないように
しましょう
Now is not the time
to become spiritually drowsy or distracted!
今は気を散らされたり
手を緩めたりする時ではありません
Remember Jesus’ words at Luke 21:36:
イエスはルカ 21:36でこう言いました
“Keep awake, then,
all the time making supplication
「それで 必ず起きる
この全てのことを逃れて
人の子の前に立つことができるよう
“that you may succeed
in escaping all these things
常に祈願をしつつ
ずっと目を覚ましていなさい」
that must occur and in standing
before the Son of man.”
By earnestly supplicating Jehovah
エホバに熱烈に祈願し
与えられる指示によく従うなら
and applying the fine direction
we are receiving,
エホバは必ず守ってくれます
we will be successful!
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcastingでした
this is JW Broadcasting.